Guide to the John Nicholas Beffel Papers TAM.055
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series I: Correspondence, 238842; 0 Linear Feet
  - Wehde, Albert: RE: Fingerprints Can Be Forged and Since Leaving Home (Letters by Beffel and Others), 1922-1937, undated; 245110 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Wehde, Albert: RE: Fingerprints Can Be forged and Since Leaving Home (Letters To/From Various People), 1923-1936, undated; 245111 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Wehde, Albert: RE: Book Since Leaving Home (Includes Partial Manuscript and Notes), 1923, undated; 245112 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Wehde, Albert: RE: Since Leaving Home (Includes Biographical Materials about Wehde), 1923-1931, undated; 245113 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Wehde, Albert: RE: Book Since Leaving Home Corrections and Mailing Lists, undated; 245114 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Wehde, Albert: Reviews of Since Leaving Home, undated; 245115 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Wehde, Albert: Related Drawings and Photographs (includes original sketches), undated; 245116 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Worthington, Dorothy, 1932-1968, undated; 245117 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Y, 1925; 245118 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Young, Art, 1920-1936; 245119 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Young, Art, 1937-1938; 245120 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Young, Art, 1939-1943, undated; 245121 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Young, Art (Letters To and From Art Young), 1916-1966; 245122 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - RE: Art Young, 1933-1966; 245123 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Z, 1926; 245124 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Zimmerman, Mary (includes photograph), 1930-1965; 245125 (Box 9, Folder 17)
- Series II: Subjects, 238847
  - Subject Files, 346474 (Box 10)
    General
    AMERICAN CIVIL LIBERTIES UNION, Beffel memorandum to A.C.L.U., 1931
    BROTHERHOOD OF UTILITY EMPLOYEES OF AMERICA, BROOKLYN LOCAL No. 102, RE: Brooklyn Edison Company 1934 35, 1939
    CENTRALIA (12 Folders):
    Affidavits (photostats)
    Correspondence: No. 1: 1920, 1922-1924, undated,
    Correspondence No. 2: 1925-1926, 1932
    Mailing lists
    Miscellaneous
    Newspaper clippings (4 Folders)
    Printed material re: Centralia
    Review bv Beffel of The American Legion Story by Moley, Jr.
    Statement and articles
    CHICAGO DAILY NEWS
    COLONIAL TIMES
    CONFEDERATED SPANISH SOCIETIES (Espana Libre)
    (7) CONTRACT PRISON LABOR
    (8) CONTROCORRENTE – MEMORIAL ISSUE (3 Folders): Articles, Correspondence with Ateo Felicani, Correspondence, General
    (9) CONVICTION OF INNOCENT PEOPLE
    (10) CREMATION
  - Contains:, 346475 (Box 11)
    DRAFT RIOTS CIVIL WAR; "ELEPHANTS AND IRISMEN," A vaudeville type act put on by Beffel at various times
    FEDERATED PRESS Correspondence, 1921
    FERRER SCHOOL: Correspondence re: Harry Kelly book and research by various people on Kelly and the Ferrer School; also "A Tribute to Harry Kelly" by Abe Bluestein, given at the Rand School, 1953
    SUHR, Richard Ford and Herman Suhr Case, 1913-1914, re: Wheatland, California riot during the hop pickers strike
    INDUSTRIAL WORIMS OF THE WORLD, Includes: "An Open Letter to President Harding – General Defense Committee, 1922 ?"
    "Who Were the Wobblies?" by Westbrook Pegler
    "Concerning the lynching of Wesly Everest and Frank Little" a statement by Beffel
    JOBS AND JOB-HUNTING: Includes letter to and from various editors, etc. about inquiries made by Beffel about positions available
    KENTUCKY MINERS DEFENSE (2 folders): Correspondence, 1937 – 39; Statements and articles
    LEAGUE FOR MUTUAL AID (LFMA), 9 Folders: LFMA 1930s; LFMA 1940s; LFMA 1950s; LF14A 1960 – 63; Anniversary Dinner Celebration, 1969 – 70; LFMA Executive Committee; LFMA Executive Committee, Finances 1940s; LFMA History by Beffel
  - Contains:, 346476 (Box 12)
    LIBRARIES: Letters generally pertaining to gifts given by Beffel to various libraries
    MARY CELESTE: Material relating to the mysterious disappearance of the crew of the ship the Mary Celeste
    MENTAL ILLNESS Material about conditions in (state) mental institutions, including personal accounts by various people
    O.R.T.A. for Dem Com (Democratic Communications)
    POSTAL WORKERS
    SACCO and VANZETTI (9 Folders):
    Notes, general items and correspondence (late 1960s) with Decker, Ann Folger; Ehrmann, Herbert B; Musmanno, Hon., Michael A.
    Printed material re: Sacco and Vanzetti
    Bibliographies
    Correspondence No. 1: 1921-1929, 1937 Correspondence No. 2: 1947, 1959–1970 Correspondence No. 3: Memorial, 1967 (Including press releases and articles)
    Re: Plays and musicals based on Sacco and Vanzetti
    Francis Russell's reply to Fred Cook re: Sacco and Vanzetti
    Gus Tyler's speech at the Sacco and Vanzetti Memorial
  - Contains:, 346477 (Box 13)
    TERZANI CASE (4 Folders): Affidavits; Correspondence, 1933 – 34; Newspaper clippings; Press releases, Memorandum
    CARLO TRESCA (10 Folders):
    Tresca Memorial Committee:
    Correspondence No. 1: 1944 – 46
    Correspondence No. 2 1947 – 48,
    Correspondence No. 3 – 1949,
    Correspondence No. 4 – 1950,
    Correspondence No. 5 1952 – 53,
    Correspondence No. 6 with Hon. Frank Hogan, 1949—50
    Undated material:
    Draft of a pamphlet on Tresca, "Murder in the Dim out" by Beffel,
    Articles, miscellaneous
    Un American Activities Committee correspondence, 1949
    TUNNELS
    UNUEMPLOYED UNION OF NEW YORK – 1931
    UNITED LIBERTARIAN ORGANIZATION: Statements and correspondence of Walter Starrett, 1937
    UNITED OFFICE AND PROFESSIONAL WORKERS OF AMERICA, Including a Local 16 flier and one letter from "M" (Margaret)
    THE WEST
    RE: Writing -- Letters pertaining to Beffel's writing; compiled by name of magazine or publication
    MISCELLANEOUS MAILING LISTS
- Series III: Writings by Beffel, 346478
  - Contains:, 346479 (Box 14)
    Short Stories (some published, 1912-1937):
    "The wanderer meets her at the edge of the wood," Nov. 6, 1912
    Altars of the Gods, November 16, 1912
    At the Foot of the Totem Pole, Dec. 13, 1923 (also entitled Never Go Back, May 6, 1935)
    The Boy Who cried Wolf, February 28, 1932
    The Camel Stealer, April 16, 1919
    Canines Met at Night
    The City of Tombs, October 24, 1912
    The Dance of Death, July 28, 1926
    The Deaths and the Lights, July 22, 1933
    Demetri, October 5, 1912
    Denmark, October 21, 1912
    Dog in the Night, September 29, 1927
    Dogs Met at Night, October 16, 1933?
    Empire Stuff (also entitled McIntyre Puts It Over) 1919?
    Fantasia
    The Farm, May 12, 1912
    Fifty Minutes from Chicago
    Gas in Area D, October 15, 1927
    A Girl in Vermont (by John Strong (pseud.)
    Ghost House
    Glad Do I Die, July 3, 1913
    Grid Patton's Dog, March 27, 1912
    Hard Sledding, April 2, 1937
    Helping Ed, February 25, 1916
    I Find a Dog (also a different version entitled Lost Dog)
    "It was a Son She Heard From Her Father's Ship..."
    The Laughter of Fairies, August 13, 1912
    Light in the Sky, November 30, 1914
    The Man Near the Stove, September 7, 1929 (also entitled They Don't Mix)
    The Man With the Black Wiskers: 3 different verions, one dated November 9, 1923
    Mean Man Mallory, January 17, 1924
    Mean Man Mallory and the Goat
    Melody's End, August 7, 1934
    Mightier Than the Machine gun
    Miracles Even Now, September 9, 1927
    Moral of Australia; Muldoon, October 1, 1912
    The Night Clerk and the Gold, begun Jan. 17, 1926; resumed Aug.17, 1926
    On Thunder Bay (also entitled Joe Chenery)
    Open That Chest! (also entitled End of the Rope and The Brass Bound Chest)
    A Queen Come Back to Haunt Me
    The Scar, August 11, 1914
    Slatko the No Good (also entitled The Hole in the Earth)
    Some Upper Room
    Son of a Crimp, August 12, 1923
    The Soup Eater Silenced at Last, February 10, 1919?
    The Trained Duck (also entitled A Thief in the Wings) Sept. 24, 1934
    Up An Alley (also called Up an Alley in Ohio) June 29, 1927
    Up the Snow Slopes of Rainier
    The Viking Woman
    West From St. Paul by Mary Starland (pseud.)
    The Wild Wild West; Waterloo
    The Youngster in Buena Terra (retired copy).
  - Contains:, 346489 (Box 15)
    "Annie Oakley" -- Includes 3 drafts of article on Annie Oakley, letters to various people concerning the article and notes by JNB on Annie Oakley
    "Burn, Black Man, Burn" -- Article written in 1943(?): Includes 3 copies of the article and notes by J"NB on that subject
    "Dark Day in New England" -- Article written for The Mercurv April 1943: Includes typescript of the article "Blackout in New England," letters to Eugene Lyons and Robert Littell, and misc. material related to the article
    "The Fauntlerov Plague": Material and article relating to a proposed statue honoring Frances Hodgson Burnett, author of Little Lord Fauntleroy. (Beffel was opposed to the building of the statue)
    "Sir Martin Frobisher": Includes first draft and final (?) draft of articles on Frobisher, notes and newspaper clippings
    Mooney, Tom: Serials of newspaper articles on Mooney written in June 1920
    Radicals I have Met: Draft of the article "Four Radicals" which was published in The American Mercur April 1932, and Includes sketches of E.V. Debs, Bill Haywood, Vanzetti, Lucy Parsons and Tom Mooney (The last sketch was deleted from the final draft of the article)
    "Stephen Crane Gets Fired": Includes copies of the article, letters to and from Edgar Snyder, notes by JNB for article and related misc. material
    "Wolheim, Master Teller of Tales": Includes draft of article, notes and questionnaires pertaining to the article; Miscellaneous Writings.
  - Contains:, 346497 (Box 16)
    American Mosaic; Light and Shadow on the Land of the Free: An outline and proposal for a book on Americana to be written by Beffel. Many of the tentative chapters have been written or published as short stories
    "Book of Light": Seems to be a diary of sorts; Julv 14, 1926 December 24, 1939
    Corn Belt Bov: A series of sketches based on Beffel's early years in Seneca, Illinois. They were intended to be part of an autobiography (?). It is believed that some of the sketches were published as separate short stories. It is alternately entitled "Honest Hearts and Willing Hands"
    Desperate Pageantrv: The saga of the Polaris Disaster. This is chapter 1 of a book never written (?)
    Jim Higgins Jail: A partial novel. 115 p.
    Land of the Free: A magazine edited and published by Beffel. It was intended as "A monthly journal which lets in light and air." (never published?)
    Living Men: Devoted to the Struggles of the Driven. A magazine edited and published by Beffel. (See Also map case for an unused design of the cover). It contained articles by various people including David Karsner, Theodore Dreiser and Robert Monov.
    Holdings: Vol. 1 No. 5 (incomplete); Chicago, October 1917, Vol. 2 No. 3,Chicago, February 1913; Vol. 2 No. 3 Chicago, June 1919; Vol. 2 No. 4, New York, October 1919
    The Wart: An incomplete story
    Where Did these Gentlemen Die?": Manuscript for a proposed book by Beffel which dealt with the mysterious deaths of various distinguished men.
  - Contains:, 346490 (Box 17)
    Billington and Colonial Families:
    Notes and manuscripts relating to John Billington, a Pilgrim who was hanged in the Plymouth Colony ten years after its founding, and to early colonial times. Also includes a small part of a manuscript by George Prince. The proposed title of Beffel's book, in 1930, was "John Billington: Pilgrim to the Gallows."
  - Contains:, 346491 (Box 18)
    Anecdotes
    Articles and Essays (2 folders), Some published: A—M, M—Z
    Book Reviews
    Letters to the Editor
    News Items and Releases (some published):
    News Items and Releases: Contains five articles for the Federated Press on marine workers, 1921
    Newspaper and Magazine Writings: Approximately 60 articles clipped from magazines and newspapers written by Beffel (Some of the articles can be found in manuscript form in the folders labeled "Articles and essays," and "Short stories")
    Notes and Memorandums
    Poems (some published)
    Collected Poems: poems by various authors, clipped and copied by Beffel
    About JNB: includes biographical notes on Beffel and 11 photos
    Miscellaneous Material.
- Series IV: Writings by Others, 346480
  - Contains:, 346481 (Box 19)
    Paul Crouch: Includes part of a manuscript by Crouch, a well known American communist, Broken Chains" later entitled "Bondage Broken"; an article by Crouch, "Top A Bomb Scientist Was a Communist," and other material relating to Crouch, including correspondence; Ennes Ellae: A complete autobiography in manuscript form by
    Ennes Ellae: A complete autobiography in manuscript form entitled "A Grain of Sand -- A Drop of Water," edited by Beffel (281 pp.). Ellae was a Dutch emigrant to the U.S. who became involved with the I.W.W. in California
    Alice M. Gray: Manuscript, including proof sheets of a draft of sorts
    Ellen Leonard: Manuscript of "Three Days of Terror"
    W.H. Long: 2 copies; one incomplete of a manuscript "Sane Sex Life and Sane Sex Living."
  - Contains:, 346492 (Box 20)
    Helen Parkhurst: Complete ms. of Parkhurst's "Child World"
    Louise Andrus Rogers: Contains 2 manuscripts: "Of Sunken Gold," a film score; "No Encores," a play: and a few letters.
  - Contains:, 346493 (Box 21)
    Contains the fragile original of Harry Kelley's manuscript "Roll Back the Years: Odyssey of a Libertarian," edited by Beffel. Kelly was a well known anarchist and co founder of the Ferrer colony in Stelton, N.J.
    NOTE: patrons must use the user photocopy of this manuscript which is housed in boxes 26 and 27.
    For additional information, see the subject folder "Ferrer School" in Box 11. (This manuscript contains some photocopies from the Beffel collection at Wayne State University, Archives of Labor History and Urban Affairs.)
  - Contains:, 346494 (Box 22)
    Contains manuscript (complete?) of G.P. Maximoff's book of Bakunin's works, edited by Beffel, titled Bakunin's Political Philosophy: His writings on Scientific Anarchism. The manuscript also includes a biographical sketch of Bakunin by Max Nettlau and an introduction by Rudolf Rocker. Also included are a few letters to and from Olga Maximoff Urkevich, Rudolf Rocker and Boris Yelensky.
- Series V. Family Files (unprocessed), 346483
  - Family Files, 346484 (Box 23)
  - Family Files, 346495 (Box 24)
  - Family Files, 346496 (Box 25)
- Series VI: User photocopies from Series IV (Writings by Others), 346485
  - Contains: User photocopy (part 1) of Harry Kelley's manuscript "Roll Back the Years: Odyssey of a Libertarian," edited by Beffel., 346486 (Box 26)
  - Contains: User photocopy (part 2) of Harry Kelley's manuscript "Roll Back the Years: Odyssey of a Libertarian," edited by Beffel., 346487 (Box 27)
- Series VII: Addendum (unprocessed), 346488
  - Box 28, 584701
  - Box 29, 584702
  - Box 30, 584703
  - Box 31, 584704
  - Box 32, 584705
  - Box 33
  - Original art and prints, 1908-1945; 1 Linear Feet (Box 33, Box MSOS007, Folder 1, Box MSXOS001)